Guide to the Jean Anouilh Manuscripts
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Jean Anouilh manuscripts
1924-1977
GEN MSS 459
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.25
(3 boxes)
Manuscripts of several plays by Anouilh, including L'invitation au chateau, along with many examples of juvenilia (short plays and a school essay), a group of scenarios for a cinema commercial, and notebooks.
Anouilh, Jean, 1910-1987
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired by purchase from a private collection, on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 1999.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Existence and Location of Copies
Microfilm available.
JEAN ANOUILH (1910-1987)
Jean Anouilh, the French playwright, was born in Bordeaux on June 23, 1910. He came to prominence as early as 1932 with the success of L'hermine at the Théâtre de l'Oeuvre in Paris, and for the next five decades his name was never absent from the French and international stage. He is the author of more than 40 plays, which he has published thematically as Pièces roses, Pièces noires and Nouvelles pièces noires (including "Antigone", one of his most performed works), Pièces brillantes (including "L'invitation au château", rendered in English as "Ring Round the Moon"), Pièces grinçantes (including "La valse des toréadors") and Nouvelles pièces grinçantes, Pièces costumées, Pièces baroques (including "Cher Antoine" and "Ne réveillez pas Madame"), and Pièces secrètes. Anouilh also wrote translations of Shakespeare, Oscar Wilde, and Graham Greene, as well as more than a dozen screenplays, several ballets, and television adaptations. He died suddenly in Lausanne, Switzerland, on October 3, 1987.
Scope and Contents
The Jean Anouilh Manuscripts consist of drafts of Anouilh's plays from various times in his career, including many juvenilia. Included are various notebooks and several other non-dramatic pieces. The collection has been organized into one series, Manuscripts, and spans the years 1924-1977.
Manuscripts consists principally of drafts of Anouilh plays, from the early short works, "Mondor et Tabarin" and "Billets de Banque", to his later, better-known works, such as "Cher Antoine". Present in this collection are a number of draft sections, such as those for "L'invitation au château", which differ from the printed versions. Also included are several occasional pieces, such as a group of scenarios intended for cinema commercials for a lotion, "O'cap", and an introduction to a French translation of the Kleist play, "L'ordalie ou la petite Catherine de Heilbronn" [originally "Das Käthchen von Heilbronn"].
Accompanying each manuscript is a folder of "cataloger's notes", which usually also include a transcript. These were prepared for the seller before the material arrived at Yale. They have been retained in the collection because they contain valuable contextual information, but they are not presented as being definitive.
French drama -- 20th Century; Anouilh, Jean, 1910-1987
- Manuscripts, 1924-1977; 1.25' (3 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Manuscripts are arranged alphabetically by title.
  - ANTIGONE
    - Draft, typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Cataloger's notes, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Printed version, annotated, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Reading copy of Monelle Valentin
    - Cataloger's notes, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - L'ARTICLE QU'IL NE FALLAIT PAS FAIRE
    - Draft, holograph, corrected, [1941] (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Cataloger's notes and transcript (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - BILLETS DE BANQUE
    - Draft, holograph, corrected, 1928 Jun (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Cataloger's notes and transcript (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - CHANSON DE ROLAND
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: Le jeune homme et la lion, Box 2, folder 38
  - LES CHATS
    See: Les demoiselles de la nuit, Box 1, folder 25
  - CHER ANTOINE
    - Script, typescript carbon, annotated with stage directions and blocking, [1967] (Box 1, Folder 9-11)
      Includes telegrams to JA from Simone Berriau and Maria Sommer, both 1969 Oct 1
    - Cataloger's notes, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Notes with draft of scene, holograph and typescript, corrected, ca. 1967 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Cataloger's notes and transcript (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - COMPOSITION FRANCAISE
    - Draft, typescript, corrected, ca. 1960 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Cataloger's notes, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - CONTACTS
    - Notes with draft of first tableau, holograph, corrected, ca. 1930-31 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Cataloger's notes and transcript (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - LA CULOTTE
    - Script, typescript mimeograph, annotated with stage directions and blocking, ca. 1977 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Cataloger's notes, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - LA DAME QUI FAIT DES MARIAGES
    - Draft fragment, holograph, corrected, ca. 1928 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Cataloger's notes and transcript (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - DE LA CULTURE ET DE LA BOUILLON
    - Draft, holograph, corrected, [1960] (Box 1, Folder 23)
      Introduction to staging of "Becket"
    - Cataloger's notes and transcript (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - LES DEMOISELLES DE LA NUIT & LES CHATS
    - Notes, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Cataloger's notes and photocopy (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - LES DEUX COCUS
    - Draft, holograph, corrected, ca. 1927 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Cataloger's notes and transcript (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - LA FOLLE DE CHAILLOT
    - Draft section, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Cataloger's notes and transcript (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - GALIGAï
    - Synopsis drafts, holograph, corrected, ca. 1975 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Cataloger's notes and transcript (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - L'INVITATION AU CHATEAU
    - Notes, ca. 1945 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Draft sections, holograph and typescript, corrected, ca. 1945 (Box 2, Folder 34-36)
    - Cataloger's notes, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - LE JEUNE HOMME ET LA LION [CHANSON DE ROLAND]
    - Draft sections, holograph, corrected, ca. 1970 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Cataloger's notes and transcript (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - MANDARINE
    - Draft, holograph, corrected, ca. 1930-31 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Cataloger's notes and transcript (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - MONDOR ET TABARIN
    - Draft, holograph, corrected, 1924 Jun (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Cataloger's notes and transcript (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - NE RÉVEILLEZ PAS MADAME
    - Draft sections, holograph and typescript, corrected, ca. 1964 (Box 2, Folder 44-45)
    - Notes, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Cataloger's notes and transcript (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - O'CAP
    [Scenarios for cinema commercials for O'cap lotion]
    - Draft, holograph, corrected, ca. 1930 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Cataloger's notes and transcript (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - L'ORDALIE OU LA PETITE CATHARINE DE HEILBRONN
    - Introduction (to the play by Heinrich Von Kliest), drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected, ca. 1966 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Cataloger's notes, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - PAUVRE BITOS
    - Printed version, annotated, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 52)
      Reading copy of Jean Anouilh
    - Cataloger's notes, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 52a)
  - LA PENSETTE DE JULIO
    - Notebook, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Cataloger's notes and transcript (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - LA POLKA DES LAPINS
    - Notebook, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Cataloger's notes and transcript (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - ROMÉO ET JEANNETTE
    - Notebook, ca. 1938 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Cataloger's notes and transcript (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - Draft sections, typescript, corrected, with notes, ca. 1938 (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - Cataloger's notes and transcript (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - STELLA
    - Draft, holograph, corrected, ca. 1930 (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Cataloger's notes and transcript (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - LE VERBE S'EST FAIT CHAIR
    - Draft sections, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Cataloger's notes and transcript (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - UNTITLED MANUSCRIPTS
    - [Dissertation: school essay on Classical tragedies]
      - Holograph, with teacher's comments, ca. 1926 (Box 3, Folder 65)
      - Cataloger's notes and transcript (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - [Notebook with many notes concerning "Cher Antoine"]
      - Notebook with clippings and photograph, ca. 1965 (Box 3, Folder 67-69)
      - Cataloger's notes and transcript (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - [Notebook with various notes]
      - Notebook, ca. 1950 (Box 3, Folder 71)
      - Cataloger's notes and transcript (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - [Play concerning an author and an actress]
      - Draft fragments, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 73)
      - Cataloger's notes and transcript (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - [Play concerning a character named "Liane"]
      - Draft fragment, holograph, corrected, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 75)
      - Cataloger's notes and transcript (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - [Play set in the Tuileries gardens]
      - Draft fragment, holograph, corrected, ca. 1925 (Box 3, Folder 77)
      - Cataloger's notes and transcript (Box 3, Folder 78)
    - [Poem with various notes]
      - Holograph, corrected, ca. 1925 (Box 3, Folder 79)
      - Cataloger's notes and transcript (Box 3, Folder 80)